A Finding Aid to the Nancy Kelker Research Material Regarding Mel Casas, 1890-circa 2011, bulk 1968-2005, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Nancy Kelker research material regarding Mel Casas
1890-circa 2011
bulk 1968-2005
Archives of American Art
Kelker, Nancy L.
AAA.kelknanc
Archival Resource Key
1.3 Linear feet
0.001 Gigabytes
The Nancy Kelker research material regarding Mel Casas measures 1.3 linear feet and 0.001 GB dates from 1890 to circa 2011 with the bulk of the collection dating from 1968 to 2005. The material includes sound and video recordings of interviews with Casas by Kelker and Vincent Valdez, and a talk by Casas at Georgia Southwestern University; research files that include Casas' business and legal records, correspondence, exhibition records, photographs, and student papers about Casas; and printed materials consisting of clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, journals, newsletters, and posters relating to Casas' activities during his career. One interview transcript is in digital format. The material was compiled by Kelker for the book Mel Casas: Artist as Cultural Adjuster.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Nancy Kelker research material regarding Mel Casas was donated in 2016 by Nancy Kelker.
Conditions Governing Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C., Research Center. Use of archival audiovisual recordings and born-digital records with no duplicate copies requires advance notice.
Biographical / Historical
Nancy Kelker (1951- ) is an art historian in Murfreesboro, Tennessee. and the author of Mel Casas: Artist as Cultural Adjuster.
Mel Casas (1929-2014) was a painter and educator in San Antonio, Texas. Casas was a member of Con Safo, an organization that promoted Chicano concepts and the Chicano art movement. Humanscapes, Casas' series of 150 paintings, was produced between 1965 and 1989 and has been exhibited throughout the U.S. and Mexico. Casas died in San Antonio, Texas. in 2014.
Scope and Contents
The Nancy Kelker research material regarding Mel Casas measures 1.3 linear feet and 0.001 GB and dates from 1890 to circa 2011 with the bulk of the collection dating from 1968 to 2005. The material includes sound and video recordings of interviews with Casas by Kelker and Vincent Valdez, and a talk by Casas at Georgia Southwestern University; research files that include Casas' business and legal records, correspondence, exhibition records, photographs, and student papers about Casas; and printed materials consisting of clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, journals, newsletters, and posters relating to Casas' activities during his career. One interview transcript is in digital format. The material was compiled by Kelker for the book Mel Casas: Artist as Cultural Adjuster.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as three series.
Series 1: Interviews and Talks, 1999-2005 (Box 1; 4 folders, ER01; 0.001 GB)
Series 2: Research and Project Files, 1978-2001 (Box 1; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 3: Printed Materials, 1890-circa 2000 (Box 1, OVs 2-4; 0.5 linear feet)
Chicano movement; Mexican American art; Interviews; Lectures; Sound recordings; Video recordings; Latino and Latin American artists; Casas, Mel, 1929-2014; Valdez, Vincent
- Interviews and Talks, 1999-2005; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 4 Folders Box 1; 0.001 Gigabytes ER01
  Scope and Contents
  The series includes sound and video recordings of interviews of Casas by Kelker and Vincent Valdez, as well as a talk by Casas at Georgia Southwestern University.
  - "Is it Art?," Talk by Casas at Georgia Southwestern University, April 19, 1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Includes one video recording and transcript of Casas' talk that includes Casas speaking about his childhood and how it impacted his art.
  - Casas Interviewed by Vincent Valdez, circa 2000; Archival Resource Key; 1 Sound cassettes (microcassette) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Casas Interviewed by Kelker, May 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Includes born-digital records, see ER01
  - Transcript of Casas Interviewed by Kelker (May 2000), Digital Document, Archival Resource Key; 0.001 Gigabytes One computer file (Folder ER01)
  - Casas Interviewed by Kelker by Phone, 2005; Archival Resource Key; 2 Sound cassettes (microcassette) (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Research and Project Files, 1978-2001; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 0.4 Linear feet Box 1
  Kelker's research files consist of Casas' business and legal records containing contracts, price lists, loan agreements, printed material, correspondence, and records concerning legal disputes; correspondence; and an exhibition file for Chicano Art: Resistance and Affirmation, or CARA. Other files are Kelker's correspondence, appendix material, photographs of Casas and artwork, and student papers about Casas.
  - Appendix Material, circa 2011; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Includes labeled photographs of artwork, material on Con Safo, and descriptions for Casas' Humanscapes series.
  - Business Records, 1988-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6-10)
    Includes files for general business records, Carrington Gallagher Gallery, Jansen-Perez Art Agents and Consultants, Joe Cosniac of Zuni Grill, and T.C. Spitts Contemporary Gallery.
  - Correspondence, Casas, 1983-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
  - Correspondence, Kelker, 2000-2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Exhibition Records, 1985-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Records relate to the exhibition Chicano Art: Resistance and Affirmation (1990-1993).
  - Legal Records, 1990-1991; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Photographs, circa 1988; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Includes a portrait and snapshots of Casas with others and at exhibitions. Also includes a few photographs of artwork.
  - Student Papers About Casas, 1978; 1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Printed Materials, 1890-circa 2000; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.5 Linear feet Box 1, OVs 2-4
  The series contains booklets and brochures, clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, magazines and journals, newsletters and posters relating to Casas' career and activities.
  - Booklets and Brochures, 1983-1989; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Clippings, 1890-circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19-21)
  - Clippings, 1890-circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 2)
  - Clippings, 1890-circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 3)
  - Exhibition Announcements, circa 1988-1995; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22-23)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1968-1996; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24-25)
  - Magazines and Journals, 1970-1990; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Newsletters, 1983-1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Posters, 1973; 1989; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 4)